>> Welcome back to AM Northwest. He's an
antique appraiser who knows fascinating
facts about things many of us have never
heard of. Here to share a collection of
sculptures from Mexico, we welcome back
Gary Germer. Hi Gary. >> How you doing?
>> Good. First time doing a segment with
you. This is fun. Okay, these are very
colorful. What are they called? >> Aren't
they fun? They're called And I'm I I
apologize to all of our Hispanic
viewers here cuz my Spanish isn't great.
>> Okay.
Alebrijes.
>> Okay. They're called Alebrijes and
it means it doesn't translate. >> Oh.
>> It's just a name. And what's fun >>
That's interesting. >> What's fun about
these One of the things I think that are
fun about these is people think oh they
must have some great ancient tradition.
They don't. >> Okay. >> [laughter]
>> They're just cool to look at. >>
they go back to the 1930s. There was an
artist in Mexico City named Pedro
Linares.
And he had a fever dream. Was sick with
a fever dream and he envisioned these
fantastical creatures. >> Really? >>
And in the dream they they introduced
themselves as Alebrijes. >> Really? >>
And so he made them after he got well.
Um well at least physically well. Who
knows about the mental state. [laughter]
Um he he made them out of paper mache
back in the 1930s. And then the folks in
the Oaxaca region took it up as an art.
And and these are made these are all
hand carved and hand painted and they're
made with a wood called copal wood
which is Oaxaca's high desert. And so
the trees are old trees there and it's a
soft wood that's fairly easily carved
but then they have to let it dry and they
paint them. And they're just they're I
love them because they're just fanciful.
I know um a lot of folks sometimes pull
back on stuff that might have a deep old
religious connotation or whatever. >>
And they can have whatever connotation
>> your >> you I it to be. Is it your
spirit animal? Why, yes it is. That's your
[laughter] spirit animal. >> My spirit
animal, the rat. I love rats. Yeah.
>> Mine mine is the bat because he and
I have the same dentist in in in Mexico.
>> [laughter]
>> That's hilarious. >> But they're >>
So, when people collect them, what do
they look for? Is are there certain
artists that that paint these or >> They're
It's become a tradition. Really took off
heavily in the '60s into the 1970s. And
now it's a It's a big industry in several
villages in the Oaxaca. Oaxaca's a
real artistic area in in Mexico,
anyway. And um >> And can you only
find these in Oaxaca? >> Well, that's
where the real ones come from. And then
that's where they they they can only find
this wood there. >> real ones and fake
ones. >> Yeah. And I And unfortunately,
as anything is successful, I expect
these to be made in plastic in China at
some point, you know, technique. But the
real ones are the hand-carved
um um and hand-painted. And what you're
going to value them at what causes value
is size, >> Of course. Okay. >> There's
tourist level pieces which are small and
quickly made. And then these others where
they've added the horns, you know, you
got the and all. >> That's a rabbit with
horns. Is that what that is? >> Yeah.
He's a He's a He's a little dazed-looking
rabbit with with giant with big horns.
>> Wow. >> And I You can kind of see it
in the It shows up on the camera on that
horn. You can see the detail they put
into his fur. And on on on these other
These are all really well made.
Whereas the little the little um
I guess he's a lizard, the guy in front
of him, is not as detailed in the fur,
you >> would you pay for for
something like this? >> Well, the
tourist level ones are 50 bucks or less.
>> Okay. >> These are all artist made.
You'll look They're all artist signed
them. And unfortunately for today,
I just got these. So, I haven't researched
the artists yet. I apologize on that.
>> Oh, but they're signed.
>> But they're all artist signed. >>
Oh, Oh, very cool. >> that still so they
can see that. >> And uh then that you can
research. And certain artists do bring
more. More important is the size, how
fanciful it is, and how much detail went
into the painting. >> you give a range
though? Like is there a range of >> $200
to $1,000. You kind of top out at $1,000.
But most of them are in the two to
$400 range. >> reasonable for a collection,
right? >> Yeah. And and the amount
of work that goes into, first of all,
envisioning the creature and then carving
it. >> Right. And painting it. >> painting
it. So a lot of them you'll see that
are they have the carvers that carve it
and they work in tandem with an artist
who will do the painting. >> Oh. >>
And uh >> I mean the painting is really
intricate. >> Yeah. Really and like I
said the the beaver and the or they have
the really you can see the hair on it
and the little Look at that little hair.
>> hard to see
I don't know if you can see that, but
the like little teeny tiny little brush
strokes to show the texture of the hair.
It's really cool. You have to see these
in person. >> Yeah. And the uh and then
the the the different parts of it are
actually like they just they don't
glue them on. They'll put it on. >> Oh.
>> You know, cuz you know, for the carving
it it it adds on. So the dog he gets
his bone. >> That's very cool. >> he's
my one of my favorite ones up here is
this. >> They're all What's the one in
the front? That black >> This one here?
He's a I believe I some sort of a >>
Oh. >> bat beaver or badger not beaver
but some sort of a badger or something.
I >> I don't know. I've never a dog.
It's a dog. >> it's it's it's it's it's
a little fox. >> [laughter] >> And we
got the little little fellow here that
I love his colors. They really did quite
the quite the job with the colors. >>
would someone go about starting collecting
these? Just Do you have to go to Oaxaca
to get them? >> Well, there are you can
buy you can buy them online. There's
some importers that import them. Um of
course the best is if you can be there
and work with the artists and learn The
fellow who collected these would go to
Oaxaca every other year and he bought and
what got to know the artists and you
know, that's part part of the fun of
collecting it. know. >> Yeah. But yeah,
or you can come eventually back to us
cuz these will be for sale. Plus I have
a bunch more. >> [laughter] >> I love
it. >> Put a picture in there. >>
Okay, you always have such interesting
collections and you know, like I said
in the intro, you know such fascinating
facts about things like like I've never
even heard of these and you know so much
about them. >> Well, I just thought they
were fun and then of course did some
research on them but um >> Yeah.
>> I just I I just I I they these
I handle a lot of stuff and I appreciate
the workmanship in a lot of things.
These really speak to me. I could I
could get into collecting these. >> and I
like the origin story, too. >> [laughter]
>> Okay, so we're going to have more
information about Gary on
our website at katv.com
and we will be right back with
more and more West day right there.
Thanks, Gary.